Finding Aid for University Cellar records, 1958-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
University Cellar records
1958-1989
1969-1986
University Cellar.
87469 Bimu F10 2
Student-controlled bookstore at the University of Michigan (established 1970, ceased operation in 1987.) Minutes and memoranda of board of directors, financial records, labor negotiation files, and other subject files; and photographs.
5 linear feet in 6 boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records of the University Cellar (donor no. 7434 ) were received from Jane Self, the last manager of the bookstore, on April 28, 1987. Additional records were donated by former University Cellar employees Ken Garber (donor no. 7731 ), in October 1989 and Lisa Blake (donor no. 7434 ) in November 1989.
o further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
On September 25, 1969, more than a hundred demonstrating students occupied the University of Michigan's University Administration Building (now the Literature, Science and the Arts Building) and demanded that the University establish a student-controlled bookstore. Michigan state police were called to the campus for the first time in history to break up the demonstration and the protesters were arrested.
In response to this, and as a result of meetings held with leaders of various student organizations, the Board of Regents approved the creation of a student-controlled bookstore in September 1969. The bookstore was capitalized at $200,000, with $100,000 transferred to the store by the Board of Regents from the Student Vehicle Fund, and an additional $100,000 to be raised by way of a one-time assessment of five dollars per student to be collected in the fall of 1970.
The University wished to insulate itself from any financial liabilities the bookstore might incur, and so a separate and non-controlled corporation, The Board for the Student Bookstore, Inc., was established on April 13, 1970. The corporation was also authorized by the Regents to take over the University Discount Store, which had opened in the Student Activities Building in January 1969, and to assume that organization's liabilities.
The bookstore operated on the first floor of the Michigan Union until September 1970, when it moved to the basement. At this time the official name of the organization was changed to University Cellar, Inc.
The composition of the University Cellar's Board of Directors reflected its student origins. Of the ten-member board, six were to be students, three faculty members, and one an administrator. This arrangement proved troublesome in that it was sometimes difficult to obtain a quorum (four students and two faculty), particularly at summer meetings.
In 1974 the University Cellar outbid several companies for the right to establish a bookstore in the North Campus Commons to serve the School of Music, the College of Engineering, and the College of Architecture and Design. This also marked the last year that the bookstore received any type of financial assistance from the University.
In 1979 the hourly workers of the University Cellar voted in favor of representation by the Industrial Workers of the World. Local 660, the University Cellar's union, was the largest IWW local in the world during its existence; its members constituted approximately ten percent of the total worldwide membership of the IWW.
The Michigan Union underwent significant renovations beginning in 1980. As part of the project the University Cellar was to help assume part of the cost of the basement renovations. Initially the Board of Directors agreed to this, but membership on the board changed while the project was underway, and the new membership rejected the assumption of any renovation costs. Furthermore, the store was to face a rent increase of approximately sixty-five percent in the remodeled Union. These factors, combined with clauses in the lease agreement between the University Cellar and the Michigan Union which prohibited the former from selling any items that would place it in competition with the latter, such as insignia items of the University of Michigan, caused the University Cellar to seek a new location. An agreement was reached with the owner of the Handicraft Furniture building on the corner of Liberty and Division streets in Ann Arbor, and the bookstore left the Union for its new location in the spring of 1982.
At the Liberty Street location the bookstore was free to sell any items it deemed fit, but the store's financial picture, which had usually shown a modest profit while in the Union, darkened considerably after the relocation. Expenditures for renovations to the store, along with a location now several blocks away from the central campus area, combined to produce financial losses in every year except one. In the fall of 1986 the bookstore was refused a new line of credit, and a tentative buyout offer was accepted from the Barnes and Noble bookstore chain, which had taken the University Cellar's place in the Michigan Union. The lease on the North Campus store was transferred to Barnes and Noble, but further negotiations regarding the transfer of the main store's lease broke down. The University Cellar closed permanently on December 24, 1986. In mid-February 1987 an agreement was signed with Nebraska Books, parent company of Ulrich's Bookstore in Ann Arbor, to take over the Liberty Street location, which was subsequently reopened as Michigan Book and Supply.
The records of the University Cellar have been arranged into three series: History and background; Administrative records; and Former employees files. The bulk of the records concerns the administration of University Cellar with extensive documentation of its financial operations and labor negotiations with the Industrial Workers of the World. Included are board of directors minutes and minutes of the Store, Retail, and Operations Councils.
Subjects:
Booksellers and bookselling.; Business records.; Collective bargaining--College employees--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.StudentsSocieties, etc.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Bookstores.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Bookstores--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Division Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Interiors.; Liberty Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Michigan Union.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1971-1980.StudentsSocial life and customs1971-1980.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1981-1990.StudentsSocial life and customs1981-1990.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- History and background
  Within the History and background series is documentation of the student protest leading to the establishment of University Cellar bookstore.
  - Background, 1957-1958; 1965 (Box 1)
  - Student Book Exchange, 1958-1966 (Box 1)
  - Student Bookstore Proposal and Strike, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - University Cellar, 1970-1984 (scattered) (Box 1)
- Administrative records
  Administrative records include files for the organization's board of directors and its various councils and departments. Other records pertain to labor negotiations. These records came from two principal sources, first from the bookstore itself and later, from former employees. Most of the material from the former employees filled gaps in the collection and was therefore interfiled with the existing records of the University Cellar. In those instances where the records reflected the hand of their creator, such as the drafts of council minutes written by Lisa Blake, they have been integrated into the existing series, but maintained as separate folders, with the individual's name in parentheses as part of the folder title. The remaining material was filed in the Former Employees series under the name of the individual who created or collected the material.
  - Articles of Incorporation and Bylaws, 1970-1986; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors
    - Committees
      - Finance Committee, 1971; 1981; 1984 (Box 1)
      - Joint Committee, 1979; 1986 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1971-1986
      - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
      - 1971-1977, 5 volumes (Box 1)
      - 1975-1977, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - (Larry Pulkownik), 1977-1978 (Box 1)
      - 1980-1981, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - 1983-June 1986 (Box 1)
      - (Ken Garber), October-December 1986 (Box 1)
    - Personnel and Membership, 1972-1986 (Box 1)
    - Reports to Board, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Councils
    - Store Council
      - Financial Committee, 1981; 1983-1984 (Box 2)
      - Financial Subcommittee, 1982-1984 (Box 2)
      - Memoranda and Reports, 1980-1983; 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Minutes
        - 1979-1980 (Box 2)
        - (Lisa Blake), 1980 (Box 2)
        - 1981-1984, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Self Evaluation, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Operations Council
      - Minutes
        - 1985-1986 (Box 2)
        - (Lisa Blake), 1986 (Box 2)
    - Retail Council
      - Minutes
        - 1985-1986 (Box 2)
        - (Lisa Blake), 1985-1986; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Retail and Operations Councils: Joint Meetings
      - Minutes
        - 1985-1986 (Box 2)
        - (Lisa Blake), 1986 (Box 2)
  - Departments
    - Memoranda, 1983-1985 (Box 2)
    - Reports
      - Art Department, 1980-1985 (scattered) (Box 2)
      - Textbook Department, 1984; 1986 (Box 2)
  - Financial
    - Annual Financial Report, 1972-1986; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Annual Report to Board of Directors, 1981-1985 (Box 3)
    - Audit Report, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Book Buyback, 1984-1986 (Box 3)
    - Budget
      - 1970-1971 (Box 3)
      - 1979-1981 (Box 3)
    - Budget Monitoring
      - 1982-1984 (Box 3)
      - 1984-1985 (Box 3)
      - 1985-1986 (Box 3)
      - October-December 1986 (Box 3)
    - Cash Flow Projections, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
    - History, 1971-1986 (Box 3)
    - Inventory Calculations
      - 1982-1985 (Box 3)
      - 1986 (Box 3)
    - Loan Negotiations, 1977-1986 (Box 3)
    - Monthly Statements
      - 1980-1981 (Box 3)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 3)
      - 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - Operations Review, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Payroll
      - 1977 (Box 3)
      - 1982-1986 (Box 3)
      - 1986-1987 (Box 3)
    - Payroll Negotiations, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
    - Reports, 1983-1986 (Box 3)
      located in box 4
    - Purchases, 1985-1986 (Box 3)
    - Statements, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
    - Student Assessment Fee, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Tax Case, 1975; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Tax Exempt Status, 1970-1984 (scattered) (Box 3)
    - Reports
      - 1983-1984 (Box 4)
      - 1984-1985 (Box 4)
      - 1985-1986 (Box 4)
      - June-December 1986 (Box 4)
  - Labor Negotiations
    - Bonus Plan, 1984-1985 (Box 5)
    - Labor Contract, 1979-1986; 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Management Services Group, 1980-1985 (Box 5)
    - Meetings, 1979-1981; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1974-1986; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - New Structure Proposal, 1985 (Box 5)
    - Proposals for Contract, 1979-1980; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Publicity, 1979 (Box 5)
    - Trade Book Department Dissolution Discussions, 1981 (Box 5)
  - Legal Opinions, 1969-1970 (Box 5)
  - Marketing
    - General, 1971-1985 (scattered) (Box 5)
    - Advertising, 1978; 1985-1986 (Box 5)
    - Calendars (Box 5)
    - Customer Service, 1984; 1986 (Box 5)
    - Marketing Research Survey, 1986 (Box 5)
    - Publicity, 1984-1987 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous--Student Papers on the University Cellar, 1975; 1987 (Box 5)
  - National Association of College Stores, 1981 undated (Box 5)
  - Newsletters
    - 1977-1978 (Box 5)
    - 1979-1986 (Box 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1968-1987; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Operations, 1982 (Box 5)
  - Personnel
    - General, 1971-1985 (scattered) (Box 5)
    - Job Applications--Bookstore Manager, 1969-1970; 1976; 1982 (Box 5)
    - Job Descriptions, 1970 (Box 5)
    - Job Descriptions of Salaried Employees, 1970-1971 (Box 5)
    - Policies
      - 1970-1971 (Box 5)
      - 1973-1986 (scattered) (Box 5)
  - Photographs (Box 5)
  - Policies
    - Buying, 1981 (Box 5)
    - Pricing, Refunds, Security, Cash Handling, 1981-1986; undated (Box 5)
  - Self-Analysis and Evaluation, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Stores
    - Michigan Union
      - 1972-1974 (Box 6)
      - 1975-1979 (Box 6)
      - 1980-1982 (Box 6)
      - Renovation--Floor Plan, 1981 (Box 6)
    - North Campus Commons
      - 1974, 1982-1986 (Box 6)
      - (Lisa Blake), 1985-1986 (Box 6)
    - Relocation to East Liberty
      - General, 1980-1982 (Box 6)
      - Publicity, 1970; 1981-1982 (Box 6)
      - Renovation of East Liberty Street Store, 1981-1983 (Box 6)
  - Suspension of Operations and Trustees' Final Report, 1986-1988 (Box 6)
  - Warehouse, 1980 (Box 6)
- Former employees files
  The Former Employees series includes records collected by Ken Garber, a former University Cellar employee, in the course of researching and writing an article on the University Cellar for the Ann Arbor Observer. The article was published in two parts in the October and November 1989 issues of the Observer; copies of the article are included in the collection. In addition to Garber's own papers from his years at the Cellar, this series includes miscellaneous records of University Cellar employees Jane Queller, who worked at the store from 1980 to 1986; Lisa Blake, an employee from 1976 to 1986; and Larry Pulkownik, a University of Michigan student who served on the University Cellar board of directors from 1976 to 1980.
  - Lisa Blake, 1984-1986; undated (Box 6)
  - Ken Garber
    - Ann Arbor Observer article--draft, July 1989 (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor Observer article, October-November 1989 (Box 6)
    - "Where Are They Now?" (Box 6)
  - Jane Queller, 1979-1985 (Box 6)